Chapter 124.
The Needle.
Next morning the not yet subsided sea rolled in long slow billows of mighty
bulk and striving in the peekquad's gurgling track pushed her on like giants
palms outspread. The strong unstaggering breeze abounded so that sky and air
seemed vast outbellying sails. The whole world boomed before the wind. Muffled in
the full morning light, the invisible sun was only known by the spread
intensity of his place, where his bayonet rays moved on in stacks.
Emlazinings as of crowned Babylonian kings and queens rained over everything.
The sea was as a crucible of molten gold that bubblingly leaps with light and heat.
Long maintaining an enchanted silence, Ahab stood apart, and every time the
teetering ship loweringly pitched down her bow sprit, he turned to eye the
bright sun's rays produced ahead. And when she profoundly settled by the
stern, he turned behind and saw the sun's rearward place, and how the same
yellow rays were blending with his undeviating wake. Ha! Ha! My ship! Thou
might as well be taken now for the sea chariot of the sun. Ho ho all ye nations
before my prow. I bring the sun to you.
Yoke on the further billows. Hello a tandem I drive the sea.
But suddenly rained back by some counterought, he hurried towards the
helm, huskily demanding how the ship was heading. East sou east, sir, said the
frightened steersman. Thou liest, smiting him with his clenched fist,
heading east at this hour in the morning, and the sun a stern.
Upon this every soul was confounded, for the phenomenon just then observed by
Ahab had unaccountedly escaped everyone else, but its very blinding palpableness
must have been the cause.
Thrusting his head halfway into the binnacle, Ahab caught one glimpse of the
compasses. His uplifted arm slowly fell.
For a moment he almost seemed to stagger. Standing behind him, Starbucks
looked, and low, the two compasses pointed east, and the pequad was as infallibly going west.
But air the first wild alarm could get out abroad among the crew, the old man,
with a rigid laugh exclaimed, "I have it. It has happened before, Mr.
Starbucks. Last night's thunder turned our compasses, that's all. Thou hast
before now heard of such a thing, I take it. I, but never before has it happened
to me, sir, said the pale mate gloomily.
Here it must needs be said that accidents like this have in more than
one case occurred to ships in violent storms. The magnetic energy as developed
in the mariner's needle is, as all know, essentially one with the electricity
beheld in heaven. Hence, it is not to be much marveled at that such thing should
be. Instances where the lightning has actually struck the vessel so as to
smite down some of these spars and rigging, the effect upon the needle has
at times been still more fatal, all its loadstone virtue being annihilated, so
that the before magnetic steel was of no more use than an old wife's knitting
needle. But in either case, the needle never again of itself recovers the
original virtue, thus marred or lost.
And if the binnacle compasses be affected, the same fate reaches all the
others that may be in the ship, even were the lowermost one inserted into the Kelson.
Deliberately standing before the binnacle, and eyeing the transpointed
compasses, the old man, with the sharp of his extended hand, now took the
precise bearing of the sun, and satisfied that the needles were exactly
inverted, shouted out his orders for the ship's course to be changed accordingly.
The yards were hard up, and once more the Peekquad thrust her undaunted boughs
into the opposing wind, for this supposed fair one had only been juggling her.
Meanwhile, whatever were his own secret thoughts, Starbucks said nothing, but
quietly he issued all requisite orders, while Stub and Flask, who in some small
degree seemed then to be sharing his feelings, likewise unmuringly
acquiesced. As for the men, though some of them lowly rumbled, their fear of
Ahab was greater than their fear of fate. But as ever before, the pagan
harpooners remained almost wholly unimpressed, or if impressed, it was
only with a certain magnetism shot into their congenial hearts from inflexible Ahabs.
For a space the old man walked the deck in rolling rearies, but chancing to slip
with his ivory heel, he saw the crushed copper sight tubes of the quadrant he
had the day before dashed to the deck.
Thou poor proud heavengazer and sons pilot. Yesterday I wrecked thee and
today the compasses would fain have wrecked me. So so but Ahab is lorded
over the level load stone yet. Mr.
Starbucks a lance without a pole a top mall and the smallest of the sail
makaker's needles. quick.
Accessory perhaps to the impulse dictating the thing he was now about to
do were certain prudential motives whose object might have been to revive the
spirits of his crew by a stroke of his subtle skill in a matter so wondrous as
that of the inverted compasses. Besides, the old man well knew that to steer by
transpointed needles, though clumsily practicable, was not a thing to be
passed over by superstitious sailors without some shudderings and evil
portance. "Men," said he, steadily turning upon the crew, as the maid
handed him the things he had demanded.
My men, the thunder turned old Ahab's needles. But out of this bit of steel,
Ahab can make one of his own that will point as true as any. A bashed glances
of surviile wonder were exchanged by the sailors as this was said, and with
fascinated eyes they awaited whatever magic might follow. But Starbucks looked
away. With a blow from the top maul, Ahab knocked off the steel head of the
lance, and then, handing to the mate the long iron rod remaining, bad him hold it
upright without it touching the deck.
Then, with the maul, after repeatedly smiting the upper end of this iron rod,
he placed the blunted needle endwise on top of it, and less strongly hammered
that several times, the mate still holding the rod as before. then going
through some small strange motions with it, whether indispensable to the
magnetizing of the steel or merely intended to augment the awe of the crew,
is uncertain, he called for linen thread, and moving to the binnacle,
slipped out the two reverse needles there, and horizontally suspended the
sail needle by its middle over one of the compass cards. At first the steel
went round and round, quivering and vibrating at either end, but at last it
settled to its place, when Ahab, who had been intently watching for this result,
stepped frankly back from the binnacle, and pointing his stretched arm towards
it, exclaimed, "Look you for yourselves, if Ahab be not lord of the level
loadstone. The sun is east, and that compass swears it." One after another
they peered in, for nothing but their own eyes could persuade such ignorance
as theirs, and one after another they slunk away. In his fiery eyes of scorn
and triumph, you then saw Ahab in all his fatal pride.